John M. Eggleston Papers
University of Houston-Clear Lake Archives & Special Collections
John M. Eggleston Papers
1946-1987
1964-1969
Eggleston, John M.
2010-0007
2 linear feet (4 boxes)
University of Houston-Clear Lake Archives & Special Collections
The John M. Eggleston Papers document with reports, notes, and memorandum documenting NACA and NASA projects for which Eggleston was responsible or participated from 1946-1987.
Biographical Sketch
John Marshall Eggleston, Jr. "Jack" was born in San Francisco, CA. June 26, 1926. His father was a career Navy officer from Norfolk, where Jack was raised and graduated from Oceana High School. Jack served in WWII in the USMC participating in the USMC campaign at Okinawa in 1945 and was the sole survivor of the First Marine Division.
Jack received his BS in Aeronautical Engineering VPI, 1949, MS degree in Aeronautical Engineering from University of Virginia in 1954, and MS degree in Engineering from Princeton University in 1958. In 1949 he joined the National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics, predecessor of NASA, and was assigned to High Speed Flight Research center in Muroc, California from 1949-1951 where he worked as a flight test engineer on the early supersonic research aircraft which were then in there testing stages. He returned to the Langley Research Center as a research scientist in stability and control of aircraft and missiles in 1951. In 1958 when NACA became NASA, he became Assistant Chief of the Flight Mechanics Branch at Langley working on spacecraft reentry and rendezvous, developing techniques later used on the Gemini and Apollo missions. As a Langley representative he was a member of the first group to develop the Apollo concept.
In 1962 he transferred to the Space Task Group and moved to Houston where he helped to develop the Lunar Module concept for the Apollo program into a definitive design which would accomplish the mission. In 1963 he became Assistant Chief of the Space Environment Division composed of geologists, space physicists, cartographers and geophysicists, responsible for defining the space environment and lunar surface characteristics for design of Apollo spacecraft, lunar surface experiments, spacesuits and mission operations. From 1965-1966 NASA relocated Jack and his family to Boston allowing him to participate at MIT as a Sloan Fellow in Industrial Management. Returning to Houston in 1966 he was Deputy Chief, Lunar and Earth Sciences Division until 1971; responsible for definition of Lunar surface experiments, landing site selection and survey of orbital earth resources capability using remote sensors.
In 1968 he was assigned as Staff Assistant to Director of the Manned Spacecraft Center, involved in management techniques. He was responsible for coordinating and planning the use of Center resources in terms of Center programs, developing and recommending management techniques for planning and work implementation: serving as technical advisor to the Director, Deputy Director, and Associate Director of the Manned Space Craft Center concerning management operations, optimum planning for the utilization of R and D laboratories and facilities at the Center, and the reallocation of civil service and support contractor manpower to support the technical programs of the Center.
He completed his career at JSC serving as assistant to the Director of Engineering and Development from 1971-1980. As such he acted as Program Manager overseeing a staff of 800-1000 people, mostly engineers. They were collectively responsible for the development, test, and operational readiness of all subsystems in manned spacecraft (including Apollo, SkyLab, ASTP, and Space Shuttle). In 1980 Jack retired as a Civil Servant with 30 years' service in NACA and NASA having substantially contributed to the success of the United States Space Program. Jack spent the next 10 years working as a consultant with several NASA contractors, most notably Eagle Engineering. In 1988, he retired to his beloved Farm in Hanover County, Virginia where he had a very happy life riding around on his tractor until moving to Harbors Edge Retirement Community in 2006.
In his off hours, Jack was very active in the Boy Scouts of America, Sam Houston Area Council. He served as both a Troop Leader and Adult Leader Trainer, spending numerous weekends and holidays assisting at Camp Strake. He was also a founding member of and very active in the Space Center Rotary Club.
Jack passed away on Monday, February 23, 2009 in Norfolk, Virginia. He is survived by his wife of 59 years, Phyllis Holland Eggleston, also of Norfolk, VA. He was preceded in death by his son Dr. John Marshall Eggleston, III. He leaves behind 3 children Mary Allen Wylie Stang of Seabrook, TX and husband David C. Stang; Rebecca Holland Eggleston of Wake, VA and husband David A. Turner; and Robert Allen Eggleston of Norfolk, VA and wife Jana Goloff Eggleston; and son-in-law Alan D. Wylie of Seabrook, TX. He also leaves 6 grandchildren and 6 great-grandchildren.
Scope and Contents of the Records
The collection consists primarily of papers authored or co-authored by Eggleston and reports, notes, and memorandum documenting NACA and NASA projects for which Eggleston was responsible or participated, primarily the Space Environment Division. Of particular interest are the handwritten notes on the Final Apollo 11 Flight Plan and Eggleston's notes and comments collected about post-Apollo planning from various project managers and NASA Administrator George Low. Also, the donation includes a copy of his MIT Alfred P. Sloan School of Management M.S. Thesis about Executive Selection & Development at NASA.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into seven series:
Series I: Books
Series II: Papers (Authored)
Series III: Photographs
Series IV: Langley
Series V: Mercury Series VI: Gemini
Series VII: Apollo
Access Restrictions
Unrestricted
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Eggleston, John M. (John Marshall); Low, George M., 1926-1984; Thompson, Robert F.
Subjects (Organizations)
United States. National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics; United States. National Aeronautics and Space Administration
Subjects
Bell X-1 (Supersonic plane); Project Apollo (U.S.); Project Gemini (U.S.); Project Mercury (U.S.)
Places
Langley Air Force Base (Va.); Langley Research Center
Acquisition Information
Materials donated by Mary Allen (Eggleston) Stang on June 21, 2010.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series I: Books
  - Casey Jones Cyclopedia of Aviation Terms, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Flight Testing Conventional and Jet-propelled Airplanes, by Benson Hamlin, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Survey of Lunar Surface Measurements Experiments and Geologic Studies, Contract NAS 9-2115 Final Report (Texas Instruments), Aug 30, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Exploring Space with A Camera, NASA SP-168, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II: Papers (Authored)
  - The Application of Eigenvalues (Characteristics) to the Solution of Multi-Degree Complex Systems, 30 Aug 1956 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Theoretical Calculation of the Power Spectra of the Rolling and Yawing Moments on a Wing in Random Turbulence (with Franklin W. Diederich) NACA Report 1321. (stamped author's personal copy) with Errata insert, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - A Method for the Calculation of the Lateral Response of Airplanes to Random Turbulence (with William H. Phillips) NACA Technical Note 4196, Feb. 1958 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Piloted Entries into the Earth's Atmosphere (with Donald C. Cheatham); Presented at the National Summer Meeting of the Institute of the Aeronautical Sciences. Marked personal copy, June 16-19, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Lecture on Elementary Equations of Motion (copy), 19 Oct 1959 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - A Review of Current Energy Management Studies at NASA / SAE Committee A-18, June 14-16, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Establishment of Environmental Risks; presented to "Lectures in Aerospace Medicine; USAF School of Aerospace Medicine, Brooks AFB, Texas., 3-7 Feb. 1964 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Contributions of MSC Personnel to the Manned Lunar Exploration Symposium (Section 3. "Spacecraft Capability for Apollo Scientific Experiments") 2 copies, 15-16 June 1964 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Space and the Moon - Photography's Challenge for Tomorrow (with John R. Brinkman; to be presented at the Society of Photographic Instrumentation Engineers), 25 Aug 1964 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Photographic Requirements for Manned Space Missions (with John R. Brinkman) A paper from the SPIE Technical Symposium, 26 Aug 1964 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Executive Selection and Development in a Large Government Agency (NASA) MS Thesis Massachusetts Institute of Technology, June 1966 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Preliminary Investigation of a Lunar Rolling Stone TM X-58007, March 1967 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Lunar Rolling Stones, by Eggleston, A. W. Patteson, J.E. Throop, W. H. Arant, and D.L. Spooner. Reprint from Photogrammetric Engineering, March 1968 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Trajectory Control for Vehicles Entering the Earth's Atmosphere at Small Flight-Path Angles (with John W. Young) NASA MEMO 1-19-59L (review copy), undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Results of Lunar Orbiter and Surveyor Data in Support of Apollo Site Selection, with John R. Sevier, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Series III: Photographs
  - Apollo 10 and Apollo 11, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Eggleston, John M., 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - NACA F86-C (FU-459), undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - NASA Lunar Images, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - NASA Marathon Basin (TX) Geological Field Trip, 3 April 1964 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - NASA Mexico Geological Field Trip, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - NASA Tours (Cartographic Laboratory & Ellington Simulated Lunar Surface), 1964; 1967 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - USAF Bell X-1 Glamorous Glennis, 1947; 1951 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - West Mansion, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Series IV: Langley
  - Principles and Applications of Gyroscopes, by William H. Phillips (with notations), undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Closed-Loop Centrifuge Simulation of Space Vehicle Performance, by Randall M. Chambers and Harold V. Doerfel. Presented at the ARS Semi-Annual Meeting, June 8-11, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - NASA Reports - A Discussion for Prospective Authors, by William H. Phillips, 3 Jan 1962 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Series V: Mercury
  - Mercury Seven-Orbit Mission Capability, Mercury Project Office Memorandum Report, 5 March 1962 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Series VI: Gemini
  - Preliminary B GT-3 Flight Plan Prepared by Flight Crew Support Division, 20 Sept 1964 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Gemini Narrative History Draft Chapter Planning the Experiments, (Grimwood), 31 July 1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Gemini Narrative History Draft Chapters The Idea of Rendezvous and Rendezvous in NASA Planning (Hacker), 19 Dec 1968 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Series VII: Apollo
  - Problems and Potentialities of Space Rendezvous, by John C. Houbolt (reprint from Vol. VII 1961 Astronautica Acta) includes Eggleston's handwritten notes on Lunar Rendezvous and Direct Lunar Landing. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Positional Uncertainties in Lunar Landmarks MSC Internal Note 65-ET-2, 5 Jan 1965 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Technical Memorandum relating to Instrumentation for Thermal Measurements on the Lunar Surface, prepared by Arthur D. Little, Inc, 20 Jan 1965 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Mission V Design Review, 26 May 1967 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - A Preliminary Evaluation of Landing Areas for Potential AAP Sites (alternate title: A Preliminary Evaluation of Landing Areas for the 17 AAP-Science Sites photographed with Orbiter V.) Rough Draft prepared by Mapping Sciences Branch., November 1967 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - An Investigation of Earthshine Lighting Conditions for Lunar-Surface Operations by Robert L. Jones; NASA TM X-58011, November 1967 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Apollo Site Selection Process (Bellcomm D. B. James), 14 Feb 1968 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Lunar Site Selection Memorandum, Feb-March 1968 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Apollo Program Evaluation of the LM Guidance System Performance over the Approach Terrain of Five of the Proposed Apollo Landing Sites, MSC Internal Note 68-EG23-03 (David A. Dyer), 6 March 1968 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Apollo 8 (AS-503) Mission Operation Report (prelaunch) M-932-68-08, 9 Dec 1968 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Notes and comments taken by Eggleston about systems engineering and post-Apollo planning, March 1969 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Final Apollo 11 Flight Plan AS-506/CSM-107/LM-5, 1 July 1969 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Apollo 11 Early EVA Alternate Flight Plan, 20 July 1969 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Mary Allen Wylie Papers:
    - The International Space Station by Mary Allen Wylie; a UHCL student project for Dr. Grady Purdue, 25 June 1987 (Box 4)
    - Report (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - ESA (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Japan / SS / Canada (Box 4, Folder 10)